Hi everyone, the topic of today's video is going to be two
wheeler insurance.
How many types of two wheeler insurance are there,
which policy should you
select according to your needs,
what are the tips and regulations
that if you follow, you will not only
save money on that policy but
you will also
get the most perfect policy according to your needs and along with that, you will have to have some
knowledge which if you have, then it will be
very easy for you while taking insurance,
your overall
experience related to insurance will be very important
and this thing is applicable in both the cases whether you are purchasing a new two wheeler
or removing the existing policy of your old two wheeler,
so make sure
you watch this video completely and that date is
being set, let's get started, but before that let's
talk about the sponsor of this video which is Kar
PM Bikes Scanner. Basically, with the
help of Kar PM Bikes, you
can properly scan your bike.  You
can diagnose,
reset, service
and also
you can access the live data of the bike and right now there is a
summer sale going on on their website in which
you will
get a flat 15% discount on all their products. So the link is in the
description to check out and now back to the
video online. So let's start
understanding the types of insurance. Two
wheeler insurance is basically of two types.
First is liability insurance and
second is comprehensive insurance. Now let's
talk about liability insurance first.
In layman terms, we
know it as third part insurance
and if you want, you
can also call it compulsory insurance because the
Government of India has made it mandatory
if you want to legally travel on the road with your two
wheeler. It is
mandatory that you must get third party insurance done. Otherwise, if you get caught, you can be
fined on its behalf. Now let's
understand why this is so and for
whose benefit third party insurance is actually implemented. This is
because third party insurance is mandatory.  Third party insurance is required
when your two wheeler causes loss to someone else
and that is necessary because
you may not be capable of paying that money, who
knows the provider of your third
party insurance policy will impose it
on your department, so now the
logic of compulsory insurance is understood, now how does it work,
it works like this, if you cause
loss to someone else and knowingly or unknowingly that
person files a claim against you, then if you want you
can pay that money yourself, or
you can ask the third party insurance company,
they will
settle it with you the day after and whatever
expenses are incurred, the company will bear it, since you will
not have to bear it, now let's talk about
one biggest catch while buying third party insurance,
which you have to stay away from, because
if you get caught in its trap, then third party
insurance will not be of any use, anyway there is
very little loss in our environment,
but if it will be less for a day, it will not be less for a day,
if you do not follow this thing, then it is that nowadays
third party insurance
policy providers give you two types of insurance.
Third party policy is available in this,
one is limited third party policy and the
other is unlimited third party policy which can
also be called standard third party policy.
What happens
in limited policy is that there is a
fixed amount, it can be 20000, 30000,
50000, 1 lakh, that is,
if the amount of third party insurance claim is more than that amount, then the
company will not pay it, that is, if
you have taken a limited third party policy of 20000
and the bill is of 1-2 lakh, then
you will have to pay whatever amount is above 20000. So suppose you are
going on a road with your scooter and you hit
someone's Lamborghini from behind,
that person files a case against you,
your policy people said that look
brother, you have kept limited third party policy for this
reason, we will pay only 20000, now the
remaining amount is 2 lakh, now 20 lakh.  What happens when you buy
this, you
always keep that thing in mind, generally there is a difference of ₹250 to
₹300, so for example, if the
limited third party insurance for your two wheeler is worth ₹800, then the
unlimited one will cost ₹1000 or ₹950, that's the only
difference and if you get caught in this small
difference, you will get caught in a
bigger one, so do
n't get caught in the limited third party policy, you should always
take an unlimited third party policy.
Now you people might be thinking that if I hit
someone's car, then he will also be
insured, then why is he filing a case against me,
why is he not filing it under his own insurance, so the
logic behind it is that he has incurred his
loss, now why should he get that thing done through his own
insurance
because if that loss is his loss and
if he gets his car repaired through his comprehensive insurance or first part insurance, then
he will not get the no claim bonus of the next year.
If the bill becomes big then
his policy premium will increase from next year, so
why will he incur loss
when the loss is his own doing, so that is why
he will make a third party claim,
thoughts that the same third party policy is very important not only to protect you from the law but also the days you will be trapped, the days will be reduced a lot, so I think the third party policy must have been
cleared, now let's move on to the
comprehensive policy, in common language we
also call the comprehensive policy as first fighting insurance
and it is not mandatory at all, it is your
choice, if you want then you can take a first party
comprehensive policy, advice wise even if you do not
take it, the Government of India or the
people do not care about it, but it is for
your benefit, how, if you have taken a
comprehensive policy and let's say
your motorcycle meets with an accident, then let's say
you will have to spend ₹50000 to cover the cost of this motorcycle, so out of
that 50 thousand,
your insurance company will give you 20 to 25000.  If you have
children, you will have to pay Rs 20,000 to Rs 25,000.
Now you must be thinking,
what's the benefit, I still have to pay half the money, and on
top of that, I am
also paying the insurance company, so why should I get it done?
Understand the logic behind it. Firstly,
half your burden is reduced. If the cost of the motorcycle is
falling between Rs 25,000 and Rs 50,000, and
your motorcycle is worth Rs 1.5 lakh, then
after removing the third party money,
your insurance will be worth Rs 1,000-1,100. Your total insurance will be worth something like Rs 2,000, in
which the third party
money is included. So, by comparison, you
paid only Rs 1,000-1,100, but you got a
claim of Rs 20,000-25,000. So, I think it's pretty
self-explanatory. It's raining.
Whenever you get caught in such a situation, it will
help you. Apart from that, if
your motorcycle gets stolen,
you will also get some amount in return, which is also called the
In-Short Declared Value.  The
company thinks that yes, your vehicle
is worth so many rupees, your motorcycle is worth so many rupees,
some part of it will be deducted and you will
get that money, so how will you get it
back? Firstly, your bike worth Rs. 2 lakh was
stolen and you are not getting it, secondly, your
bike worth Rs. 2 lakh was stolen and you are losing Rs.
80 out of that, you got Rs. 1 lakh, so I
think that is a butter deal, now you people must be thinking that
friend, what is he saying that if
my claim is of Rs. 50,000 then I will
give Rs. 25,000, why will I give Rs. 25,000, my friend has
not given any, his full
settlement was of Rs. 50,000, so your friend had
taken add-on coverage and that add-on coverage is
zero depression or nil depression, which is
also called zero deep policy in common language,
what happens in it, in that the
insurance company does not deduct any type of
depression, it is a general comprehensive
policy in which you have not taken the nil deep add-
on, in that the
insurance company covers all the plastic parts
separately.  It happens but if
I explain it in general claim terms then suppose if you
install a plastic part worth ₹100 then you will have to
pay ₹50, the company will give ₹50, if you
install a metal part then out of ₹100 the company will give ₹70-₹80 and
you will have to pay ₹20-30.
In case of rubber parts I think you will
not get any money from the insurance company, you will have to
pay for that yourself and similarly if there are
other glass parts or
some consumable items, if they get bolted, or if they get a nut, you know something like that, then you will have to
pay for that. But if you
take a zero depression plane then
most of your expenses will be covered,
you will get the entire plastic part and you will get the entire metal part.
Some companies include it in rubber,
like some companies say that it is a tyre and they will
pay according to how many variants it has and how much it has been kept in. Some companies
pay for the entire tyre in zero depression and
some companies do not pay even ₹1 for the tyre,
you will have to pay for that yourself, so you  When you are
buying insurance,
read the terms and conditions
carefully so that you have an idea about what type of claim
you are going to get in which type of situation, how much money will
you get, for what you will get and for what you will
not get. Apart from that, there are labour
charges, in zero depression
you mostly get above 50-60%, so
roughly speaking,
if you have taken a zero depression policy and
your motorcycle has
lost Rs 50,000 in an accident, then you will get between Rs 40,000 to Rs 45,000, except Rs
5,000, there are
some
consumables for nuts, bolts etc. and they will
put it because the radiator is broken, then they will
put oil on its brakes, if the brake line is not
put in then the brakes will be oiled and they also add a
little bit in labour charges, that is the
money that has to be paid, apart from that, out of the amount of Rs 5,000 that
you have to pay, Rs
3,000-4,000 will be for these things and
Your processing charge will be between ₹500 to ₹2000,
which is
also called filing charge. The insurance company also
charges you. If you have made a claim, you have to call
their customer helpline
support. After that, their
survey comes and surveys it. Then,
when it is reduced, it is re-inspected.
In some cases, it is done through photographs,
in some cases, the surveyor comes and
inspects it personally. So, the
insurance company takes the miscellaneous expenses from
you. Let's call it 2015. And
this becomes necessary because many
times, even after looking at the 2015, people
think why a false claim has been made.
Look, we should not even take a fake claim. Therefore,
some things have been made for our benefit.
Understand this, if people are taking insurance
and only 10-20 of them
are making claims, it could be any 10-20 people, it
could be you, it could be someone else.
But 100 people are making claims
and 100 people are taking insurance
and 80 people will go for claims, then the
insurance rates will go up a lot, that is
our loss, right now our insurance of ₹5000 will
then become ₹15000, so that is why it is
necessary, now
you have taken a comprehensive policy,
you have taken an add-on on the comprehensive policy, then this is
your surcharge, apart from that there is
a compulsory personal accident surcharge,
so you have to take that and there are some options in it, if you
want you can increase the amount, if you want
you can take advance for the pillion and
for the rider who is not the owner of the bike
or for the two riders, if you want then
you definitely need to take it, if you do not need it then
definitely take it,
if you do not need it then do not take it
because that extra money will be added
to your policy obviously, so this is all about the
Pal type policy, I mean there is a lot to
tell about the policies right now, but
in motorcycles  Generally, these advances are less,
so I'm talking about them.
In vehicles, advances come from all over the world,
they will be discussed on our tax channel some other time. For
now, we've understood the policy. Now let's understand what are the
things that we should keep in mind while buying a policy so that
our expenses are also limited
and when necessary, we get the actual
claim instead of running after the insurance people. So for that, let's
understand what the
first thing you should do is
if you are buying a bike and you are
insuring it with Dollar, then you should make sure
that you check a couple of places more. You can check it online
on some platform or you
can ask through any other agent offline. There should
n't be much difference in the premium. The advantage of taking insurance with Dollar is that if
you
go to buy a car tomorrow, it will be a little easier because
number one, he will have good connections with the insurance company
and he will
help you in every way in reducing the claim on
your motorcycle insurance through the insurance company. So, firstly,
it becomes your goodwill, so you will get it.  You will
get the benefit. Secondly, Dollar will generally make the
insurance for you from this insurance company,
which will have a cashless time.
Now, what is the cashless type? Cashless means that if
you are getting the insurance done from a workshop or a service center,
if they
require cashless time, then you will not have to pay any money.
If the insurance is worth Rs. 50,000 and
you have to pay Rs. 4,500 out of that, the rest will be paid by the
insurance company. So,
in case of cashless, you will have to pay only Rs. 4,500. The
rest will be settled by the insurance company and Dollar on their own.
But
if Dollar does
not have a cashless time limit from your insurance policy provider, then
you will have to pay the entire Rs. 50,000 to Dollar, then whatever Rs.
45,000 or 44 will
come to your account. So, it is a long
process, it is a very
drawn out thing. First, you are paying the money to Dollar,
then you are waiting for the
amount to be reflected in your bank. So, there is some
relief from the burden in your mind and
your money gets stuck.  ₹50000 is stuck for you
for one month, you could have done it for less money and butter,
so
buying insurance with dollar is butter, but if dollar is making a
margin of 100, 200, 400, 300, 400, then it is fine, but if dollar is
giving you insurance of 5000 for ₹8000,
then it does not make any sense, then you should
buy from somewhere else or tell dollar that look
brother, I am getting it outside for 5000, you can
give it to me for 5:30, but I will not be able to give eight, then
they generally negotiate, but
they will do it only if you say so, if you do not say so, then
they are not going to negotiate,
apart from that, if you are buying at dollar level, then the
matter is over, but if you are buying from outside, then
see that you buy a
policy from a good insurance company because there are cheap companies
too, they also provide cheap policies, they will give
you zero deposit as well,
but the actual claim will be a big expense.
Neither their surveys will not come for 10-10 days,
then they will not pass two parts, then
they will throw more tantrums, some even ask for video proof,
now it is a matter of common sense,
not everyone is like me on YouTube,
who takes out the camera on everything and
I am also not one of those people,
when I have an accident, I do not take out the
camera, the situation is such,
you are in a hidden situation, your bike
is lying on the road, you will not take out your phone and make a
video, it is a matter of common sense,
but the poor
providers are such,
and that is why I am saying that while
buying an insurance policy, if you are not buying it with dollars, then
make noise that you are
selecting a good insurance provider, generally
you go to the online platform and check their
claim resolution score, that is,
they have a score that yes brother, this
company has passed 96 claims out of the shown claims
easily, so that is a score,
if you go and check that score  If you look at the claim
settlement score, you will get to know
how good this company is and how
easily it provides these claims to its customers.
If you are taking insurance from outside or renewing your insurance on gas, then
if you are not doing it in dollars, then
you should make sure to
check the cashless options for all these things because the day an
accident happens, the day you will have to pay,
other wise, and all the
things that I mentioned about claim settlement, and
apart from that, the reputation of the company is obvious, you will
experience that if
a good company has to pay you Rs. 500-700 more in comparison to a third class company, then pay it, do
not worry because the
day you trap you, it will be less.
Now let us talk about what
precautions we should keep in mind while taking an insurance claim.
So well, the first thing is that I make
sure that you do not have to face it.
Secondly, I would say that never take fake claims
because this is your  The top of ₹200
is broken and you want it to be
changed in the insurance, then it is for the file charge, then that does
not make sense, if you are
breaking your bike on your own, there is no major
damage etc. in it, then
you will take the insurance claim, but when
you go to renew the policy again next year, then you will
not get the no claim bonus, because it is a simple matter, if you have taken the claim then
how will you get the bonus in the job
and the no claim bonus is significant, in the first
year you get 20%, then as you progress it increases to 50%,
so your insurance money will be
halved if you do not make a claim,
because you are giving internal benefit to the insurance company by making a
claim, so they will
also think of your benefit, but if you make fake
claims, then not only will your no
claim be declared, but the
premium that will come to the bank next year, this year your
insurance was made for 5000 and you have made two claims, the
amount of both is 80 thousand rupees,
so next year that insurance will be made for 8 thousand together
So don't buy fake clamps,
if it is justified then obviously you will have to buy them,
friend why have you given money
to the insurance company for taking the claim
so that when such a big expense comes then
we don't have to pay it, that is why
we have given that small amount to the insurance company
but we should not buy fake clamps,
so these are some things which if you
keep in mind then whatever is your insurance
process will be very simple and
in the section on insurance buying I explained it, I
explained it while taking the claim and
in the section on policies I explained this
content which is insurance related ISP
and a lot more detail, a
video can be made by going in depth because there is still a
lot of deep information which I could
not cover in this video, already this
video has become very long, still this is
only that surface, that is the basic level, but
I want that all
my brothers who buy two wheelers so that their money is
not wasted, so this is the basic level,
if you want to go beyond this then spend Rs. 5000 on this video  Please
like and comment that we
want a complete series, I can explain each part
properly with proper research,
if you want, it depends on you
and with date side, that was all in this video, will
meet again in some other video, till then bye bye